A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Publications and Draft Files FA1419
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Publications and Draft Files
1956-1988
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1419
10.7 Cubic Feet 25 boxes - 16 legal document containers, 8 letter document containers, and 1 oversize box
Scope and Contents
The collection contains oversize proofs and mock-ups of Ford Foundation publications, internal memos referencing edits to publications, photographs and negatives from various publications, and books from the Ford Foundation's library.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
1. Draft Files
2. Publications - Library Books
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2018 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2018:016.
Ford Foundation; Agriculture; Arts; Community development; Education, Higher; Energy policy; Housing; Humanities; International development; Journalism; Philosophy; Population; Urban development; Women's programs; World history -- 20th century
- Draft Files, 1974-1985; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Proofs and mock-ups of Ford Foundation publications created by the Art and Design Unit
  - That 51% Plus, 1978 December-1979 February (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Confronting Man's Inhumanity, 1979 November (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Poor, Rural, and Southern, 1978 December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Financial Support of Women's Programs in the 1970s, 1979 January-March (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - International Programs of Ford Foundation, 1979 February-July (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation Assistance in the Arab Middle East and North Africa, 1979 January-April (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Publications and Film Catalog, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Racial Segregation: Two Policy Views - Orfield and Taylor, 1979 July-1980 January (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Minding the Children, 1979 October-1980 January (Box 2, Folder 12-12A)
  - Board and Oversize Photograph from Minding the Children, 1979-1980 (Box 25, Folder 155)
  - The Problem of Women and Math, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Litigation on Behalf of Women, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14-16)
  - Local Initiative Support Corporation (LISC), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
  - Miami Riots, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Nine for Equality Under Law: Civil Rights Litigation, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 20-22, Box 4, Folder 23)
    Includes still images
  - Nine for Equality Under Law: Civil Rights Litigation - Voter Education Project, Inc. Photographs, 1977 March (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Photos by Archie E. Allen
  - Grass-Roots Environmentalists: A Report on Ford Foundation Assistance to Municipal Conservation Commissions, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
    Includes Ramapo Bikeways: Town of Ramapo Commission on Environmental Quality
  - Grass-Roots Environmentalists: A Report on Ford Foundation Assistance to Municipal Conservation Commissions - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Photos by Neal O'Brien - Potsdam, NY
  - Reproductions - How the Ford Foundation Makes Grants, An Interview with Willard Hertz, and A Ford Foundation Reprint from The Grantsmanship Center News, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Studying the Presidency, Hugh Heclo, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
  - Balance the Basics: Let Them Write, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - City High School: A Recognition of Progress, 1985 May (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Ford Foundation Assistance to Native Americans, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 33-35)
    Includes clippings, Navajo Community College Tsaile Navajo Nation (Arizona) - General Catalog 1977-1978
  - Universities, Government, and Research: A Report on Conversation Among University Presidents, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 36-38)
  - Working Against Hunger, 1976-1978 (Box 6, Folder 39-41)
  - New Approaches to Conflict Resolution: A Ford Foundation Report, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 42-44)
  - Widening the Mainstream of American Culture: A Ford Foundation Report on Ethnic Studies, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 45-47)
  - Photographs from the Schomburg Center, New York Public Library - Widening the Mainstream of American Culture, undated (Box 6, Folder 48)
    Includes photograph of Exhibit on Jazz in the early '60s, Danny Barker, New Orleans musician
  - Mediating Social Conflict, 1974 June-1978 August (Box 7, Folder 49-51)
  - Job #8931 - Mediating Social Conflict photographs, undated (Box 7, Folder 52)
    Resolution in Manhattan - Mediators interview complainants in a neighborhood dispute at the Institute for Mediation and Conflict Resolution in Manhattan; Spring flooding of the Meadowbrook addition neat the town of Snoqualmie; Snoqualmie Falls; Snoqualmie headwaters/Alpine Lakes area - Negatives, contact sheet, and prints
  - Sharps and Flats: A Report on Ford Foundation Assistance to American Music, 1980 January-June (Box 7, Folder 53-54)
  - Selected Chronology of the Ford Foundation, 1980 July (Box 7, Folder 55-56)
  - Women in the World: A Ford Foundation Position Paper, 1980 September-December (Box 8, Folder 57-58)
  - Student Aid and the Urban Poor, 1981 January (Box 8, Folder 59-61)
  - The Political Economy of Education - School Finance Bibliography, 1980 June-1981 April (Box 8, Folder 62-64)
  - School Finance Bibliography - Ford Foundation (00258-0469A) - 8 inch floppy, 1981 March 13 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Left-Handed Fastballers, 1981 April-August (Box 9, Folder 65-67)
  - A Tale of Three Cities, 1981 February-August (Box 9, Folder 68-69)
  - Toward a Strategy for Urban Integration, 1981 February-November (Box 9, Folder 70-71, Box 10, Folder 72-73)
  - Urban Poverty, 1983 July-September (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - Youth Unemployment and National Service, 1983 March (Box 10, Folder 75-75A)
  - Backs Against the Wall: Urban-Oriented Colleges and Universities and the Urban Poor and Disadvantaged, 1982 August-1984 January (Box 10, Folder 76, Box 11, Folder 77-81)
  - Reflections on a Multiracial Society, Franklin A. Thomas, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 82-83)
  - Too Little, Too Late: Services for Teenage Parents, 1982 August-1984 December (Box 12, Folder 84)
  - Higher Education, Development Assistance, and Repressive Regimes, 1982 December-1983 February (Box 12, Folder 85-86)
  - Minorities & Mathematics, 1981 May-1982 May (Box 12, Folder 87-88)
  - American Graduate Schools of Education: A View from Abroad, 1982 April-July (Box 13, Folder 89-91)
  - Search for a New Economic Order, 1981 June-1983 March (Box 13, Folder 92-93)
  - Current Interests of the Ford Foundation 1984-1985, 1984 April-July (Box 14, Folder 94-97)
  - Ford Foundation in West Africa, 1984 April-June (Box 14, Folder 98-99)
  - Ford Foundation in West Africa Photographs, undated (Box 14, Folder 100)
  - Ford Foundation PRI Program-Related Investments, 1981 July-1984 April (Box 14, Folder 101-102)
  - A Quest for Better Contraception: The Ford Foundation's Contribution to Reproductive Science, 1959-1983, 1984 February-1984 September (Box 15, Folder 103-105)
  - Ford Foundation Child Care Assistance, 1976 January-1981 July (Box 15, Folder 106)
  - Hispanics: Challenges and Opportunities, 1984 June-1985 July (Box 15, Folder 107)
  - Child Survival/Fair Start, 1983 June (Box 15, Folder 108)
  - Not Working: Unskilled Youth and Displaced Adults, 1983 June (Box 15, Folder 109)
  - Refugees and Migrants: Problems and Program Responses, 1982-1983 (Box 15, Folder 110)
  - Civil Rights, Social Justice and Black America, 1984 January (Box 15, Folder 111)
  - Women, Children, and Poverty in America, 1984 December (Box 15, Folder 112)
  - Dancing, 1982 June-1984 March (Box 15, Folder 113, Box 16, Folder 114-118)
  - Dancing - Photographs, 1982-1983 (Box 16, Folder 119)
  - Communications Network in Philanthropy, 1983 August (Box 16, Folder 120)
  - ArtWork Tapestries Photograph, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 121)
- Publications - Library Books, 1956-1988; 2
  Arranged by Library of Congress Classification (LCC)
  - Philosophical Explanations, Robert Nozick, 1981 (Box 17, Folder 122)
  - Yugoslavia at the Paris Peace Conference: A Study in Frontiermaking, Ivo J. Lederer, 1963 (Box 17, Folder 123)
  - The Nationality Question in Soviet Central Asia, Edward Allworth (ed.), 1973 (Box 17, Folder 124)
  - Hill Farms and Padi Fields: Life in Mainland Southeast Asia, Robbins Burlin, 1965 (Box 17, Folder 125)
  - Chinese Thought and Institutions, John K. Fairbank (ed.), 1957 (Box 18, Folder 126)
  - Where Women Work: A Study of Yoruba Women in the Marketplace and in the Home, Museum of Anthropology, University of Michigan No. 53, Niara Sudarkasa, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 127)
  - U.D.I.: The International Politics of the Rhodesian Rebellion, Robert C. Good, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 128)
  - Salvation and the Savage: An Analysis of Protestant Missions and American Indian Response, 1787-1862, Robert F. Berkhofer, Jr., 1972 (Box 18, Folder 129)
  - Essays from Both Sides of the Border: Mexico in Transition: Implications for U.S. Policy, Susan Kaufman Purcell (ed.), 1988 (Box 18, Folder 130)
  - Negotiating with the Chinese Communists: The United States Experience, 1953-1967, Kenneth T. Young, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 131)
  - The Puerto Rican Struggle: Essays on Survival in the U.S., Clara E. Rodriguez (ed.), Virginia Sanchez Korrol (ed.), and Jose Oscar Alers (ed.), 1980 (Box 19, Folder 132)
  - The Negro Potential, Eli Ginzberg, 1956 (Box 19, Folder 133)
  - Employment, Race, and Poverty: A Critical Study of the Disadvantaged Status of Negro Workers from 1865 to 1965, Arthur M. Ross (ed.) and Herbert Hill (ed.), 1967 (Box 19, Folder 134)
  - Haiti - Today and Tomorrow: An Interdisciplinary Study, Charles R. Foster (ed.) and Albert Valdman (ed.), 1984 (Box 19, Folder 135)
  - Time for Decision: The United States and Puerto Rico, Jorge Heine (ed.), 1983 (Box 20, Folder 136)
  - Education for Public Responsibility, 14 Eminent Americans Write of the Moral and Political Challenges that Face Our Country Today, C. Scott Fletcher (ed.), 1961 (Box 20, Folder 137)
  - In the Human Interest: A Strategy to Stabilize World Population, Lester R. Brown, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 138)
  - Population, Labor Force, and Long Swings in Economic Growth: The American Experience, National Bureau of Economic Research Inc., General Series No. 86, Richard A. Easterlin, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 139)
  - Population Factors in Development Planning in the Middle East, Frederic C. Shorter (ed.) and Huda Zurayk (ed.), 1985 (Box 20, Folder 140)
  - Studies on the Population China, Ping-ti Ho, 1368-1953, 1959 (Box 21, Folder 141)
  - Population Change in Southeast Asia, Wilfredo F. Arce (ed.) and Gabriel C. Alvarez (ed.), 1983 (Box 21, Folder 142)
  - Egypt: Population Problems & Prospects, Abdel R. Omran (ed.), 1973 (Box 21, Folder 143)
  - Income-Tested Transfer Programs: The Case for and Against, Irwin Garfinkel (ed.), 1982 (Box 21, Folder 144)
  - Shifting Responsibilities: Federalism in Economic Development, DeWitt John, 1987 November (Box 22, Folder 145)
  - The Reagan Record: An Assessment of America's Changing Domestic Priorities, John L. Palmer (ed.) and Isabel V. Sawhill (ed.), 1984 (Box 22, Folder 146)
  - Business and Academia: Partners in New England's Economic Renewal, John C. Hoy (ed.) and Melvin H. Bernstein (ed.), 1981 (Box 22, Folder 147)
  - Economic Opportunity in the Ghetto: The Partnership of Government and Business, Sar A. Levitan, Garth L. Mangum, and Robert Taggart III, 1970 (Box 22, Folder 148)
  - Public Policy and Private Enterprise in Mexico, Raymond Vernon (ed.), 1964 (Box 22, Folder 149)
  - Scheming for the Poor: The Politics of Redistribution in Latin America, Wiliam Ascher, 1984 (Box 22, Folder 150)
  - Industrial Society in Communist China: A Firsthand Study of Chinese Economic Development and Management - with Significant Comparisons with Industry in India, the USSR, Japan, and the United States, Barry M. Richman, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 151)
  - Planning and Economic Policy in India, D.R. Gadgil, 1972 (Box 23, Folder 152)
  - The Economic Development of Bangladesh: Proceedings of a Conference held by the International Economic Association at Dacca, E.A.G. Robinson (ed.) and Keith Griffen (ed.), 1974 (Box 24, Folder 153)
  - Institution Building in India: A Study of International Collaboration in Management Education, Thomas M. Hill, W. Warren Haynes, and Howard Baumgartel, 1973 (Box 24, Folder 154)